I'm going to leave.
Me voy a ir.
I have to leave.
Tengo que hacerlo.
I said I'm going to leave.
Dije que me voy.
I...
Yo…
MURA
MURA
Judong woke up.
Judong despertó.
Did he wake up?
¿Se despertó?
You should go.
Deberías ir.
I can see the end now.
Pero ver cómo terminará.
Show me the sacred stone when you find it.
Muéstrame la piedra sagrada cuando la encuentres.
It's probably another one of those things that only you guys can see.
Debe ser otra cosa que solo ustedes pueden ver.
You're right.
Tienes razón.
I'm going to leave soon, and you belong to this world.
Me iré pronto y tú perteneces a este mundo.
So we should not waste time being each other's happiness.
No deberíamos perder el tiempo siendo la felicidad del otro.
We should not mistake fake wings...
No deberíamos pretender
for wings that can fly.
que esto es algo posible.
Habaek!
¡Habaek!
Hey.
Hola.
My gosh!
Dios mío.
-Hospital? -That's right.
- ¿Qué? - Así es.
When I woke up, I was at the hospital.
Desperté en el hospital.
A passerby saw me
Un transeúnte me vio y me llevó ahí.
I had no idea who I was or what happened.
No sabía quién era ni nada. No podía recordar nada.
That man left his contact information,
El transeúnte dejó su información,
so I called him thinking he might know something
así que lo llamé para ver si sabía algo, pero no pude contactarlo.
Then how did you end up at the temple?
¿Y cómo llegaste al templo?
I wandered around like a homeless guy after leaving the hospital.
Al salir del hospital, deambulé por las calles.
Then I worked in a salt field in the south for a while.
Luego trabajé cosechando sal,
I also worked at a donkey farm, a perilla leaf farm, and a larva farm.
en granjas de burros, de hojas de perilla y de larvas.
I sailed for a bit too. Then I sold supplements.
Navegué un poco y vendí suplementos.
"Kids, go away. This is very rare.
"Niños, váyanse. Esto es muy raro.
If you take this, your head, shoulders, knees, and back..."
Si toman esto, sus cabezas, rodillas…".
I followed the seller around for a while, then I somehow ended up at the temple.
Seguí al vendedor por un tiempo y terminé en el templo.
I know you passed out because of Biryeom's thunderbolt,
Sé que te desmayaste por el rayo de Biryeom,
but I don't understand how it wiped out all your memories.
pero ¿cómo perdiste tus recuerdos?
It was Mr. Shin's doing.
Fue el señor Shin.
He confessed to Biryeom.
Se lo confesó a Biryeom.
Where's the sacred stone?
¿Y la piedra sagrada?
Finally...
Por fin.
Oh, no. Have you guys seen my tablet?
Vaya, ¿han visto mi amuleto?
Hey, you brought it here?
¿Lo trajiste aquí?
-Why on earth did you bring it? -I was told to bring it here.
- ¿Por qué? - Me dijeron que lo hiciera.
-You didn't bring yours either? -No.
- ¿No trajeron los suyos? - No.
Why would we? It's of no use here.
¿Por qué? Aquí no funcionan.
Habaek is one thing, but you're such a bonehead too.
Sí que eres un cabeza dura.
Jeez, I knew I was forgetting something.
Sabía que olvidaba algo.
Where did I lose it?
¿Dónde lo perdí?
It's not your home. Why must you go back there every day?
No es tu casa. ¿Por qué regresas cada día?
And why are you following him?
¿Y por qué lo sigues?
Just stay with us. It's not like you'll be here for much longer.
Mejor quédate con nosotros.
I heard Habaek's place has no walls.
Oí que la casa de Habaek no tiene paredes.
The walls at you and your husband's place make me claustrophobic.
Las paredes en la casa de tu esposo me dan claustrofobia.
What?
¿Qué dijiste?
Have you lost your mind? My husband?
¿Te volviste loco? ¿Mi esposo?
Biryeom said you two are engaged but haven't spent the night together yet.
Biryeom dijo que aún no pasaban la noche juntos.
I remember him saying he wants to get it done--
Dijo que ya quería…
Hey!
¡Cállate!
Do you want to get your tongue crushed?
¿Quieres que te congele la lengua?
By the way, Biryeom has been acting a little strange.
Biryeom ha estado actuando raro.
He's been overly sensitive and hostile toward Mr. Shin.
Se está comportando muy hostil con el Sr. Shin.
It also looks like he's purposely trying to provoke him.
Parece que intenta provocarlo.
I get that he can't be fond of him,
Entiendo que no le agrade,
but there's no need for him to be so obvious about despising him.
pero no tiene que ser tan obvio.
I mean, this isn't the divine realm.
No estamos en el reino divino. Aquí no importa.
You said he's the one who did that to Judong.
Dijiste que él atacó a Judong.
but it wasn't intentional.
pero no fue intencional.
He probably did it without realizing it because he was thrown off.
Debió hacerlo sin querer por la confusión.
Biryeom thinks that it was intentional.
Biryeom cree que fue intencional.
I'm worried that he might end up causing trouble.
Me preocupa que cause problemas.
By the way, is that man a human being or a god?
Por cierto, ¿el Sr. Shin es un ser humano o un dios?
-We can't harm him if he's human. -That's why I'm worried.
- No podemos lastimarlo si es humano. - Por eso estoy preocupada.
-Is this where you live? -Yes. This way, please.
- ¿Aquí viven? - Sí, pase por aquí.
Ms. Descendant must be home already.
Ya debe haber llegado.
I like this place. Where is the owner of this house?
Me gusta este lugar. ¿Dónde está la dueña?
Should I bring her?
¿La llamo?
Leave her alone. I think she's asleep.
No la molestes. Creo que está durmiendo.
She'll be happy to hear you've found your sacred stone.
Le alegrará saber de la piedra sagrada.
Please excuse me.
Con su permiso.
Divine servants?
¿Sirvientes divinos?
When Biryeom talked the Queen Mother into establishing that custom,
Cuando Biryeom le propuso esa costumbre a la Reina Madre,
many gods were against it.
muchos dioses se opusieron.
Mura was one of them.
Mura estuvo entre ellos.
They thought it was unfair
Pensaron que era injusto
to make humans take responsibility for what gods did.
que los humanos se hicieran cargo de lo que hacían los dioses.
-Are you okay? -With what?
- ¿Estás bien? - ¿Por qué preguntas?
I'm talking about the divine servants.
Por los sirvientes divinos.
I know you tried your best to forget about it.
Sé que has intentado de todo para olvidarlos.
You've heard about the divine servants, right?
Ha oído de los sirvientes divinos, ¿no?
Humans who made a pledge to serve us generation after generation.
Son humanos que prometieron servirnos.
If you run into problems, find descendants of that family.
Si tienes problemas, busque a sus descendientes.
I'm not sure if the High Priest should continue
No sé si el sumo sacerdote
to play along with you, pretending not to remember--
debería seguirte el juego de que no recuerdas nada…
I have completely erased it from my mind.
Lo borré por completo de mi mente.
The moon has waxed and waned 1,200 times.
Han pasado 1200 años desde entonces.
Whether you overcome it or just endure it,
Si lo superé o solo lo aguanté,
it simply doesn't matter anymore after that much time has passed.
ya no importa después de tanto tiempo.
The High Priest...
El sumo sacerdote
should know that much.
debería saberlo.
Why do you seem so down when you've found all the sacred stones?
¿Y por qué estás tan triste si ya hallaste las piedras sagradas?
And what's with Mura?
¿Y qué hay con Mura?
She's dying to send you back.
Se muere por enviarte de vuelta.
She has asked me so many times already.
Ya me lo ha pedido muchas veces.
Heading out already?
¿Ya te vas?
Yes, I have to do something.
Sí, estoy ocupada.
Bye.
Nos vemos.
BLESSED MENTAL HEALTH
SANTA SALUD MENTAL
Why is the door open? My gosh!
¿Por qué está abierta la puerta?
Why are you so early today?
¿Por qué llegaste tan temprano?
Hey, look.
Mira la hora.
You're just all talk.
Mucho ruido y pocas nueces.
I thought you usually get here when the morning star is still up.
Creí que siempre llegabas con el lucero del alba.
-Is something wrong? -Yes, obviously.
- ¿Pasó algo? - Sí, claramente.
We promised each other that we'd work hard.
Prometimos trabajar duro. ¿Cómo llegas a esta hora?
We open at 10 a.m.
Abrimos a las 10:00 a. m.
Be quiet. Starting today, we'll open at 8 a.m.
Desde hoy, trabajaremos de 8:00 a 20:00.
We'll be open on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday evenings.
Y día por medio hasta más tarde. Publícalo.
Okay.
De acuerdo.
-What's that? -It's from Mr. Ma.
¿Y eso?
I don't believe that. I'm sure it's for me.
No te creo. Seguro es para mí.
Shouldn't you know him better by now?
¿No deberías conocerlo ya?
Do you want to read the reviews online?
¿Quieres ver las reseñas?
We have so many new bad reviews.
- Tenemos muchas malas. - Olvídalo.
Try one. You can just suck it.
Prueba uno. Debes chuparlo.
I don't want it.
No quiero.
Come on. Try it.
Vamos, pruébalo.
Enjoy.
Disfruta.
Sang-yu worries about you more than you worry about yourself.
Sang-yu se preocupa por ti más que tú misma.
I'm going to leave. I have to leave.
Me voy a ir.
I said I'm going to leave.
Dije que me iré.
MR. SHIN HU-YE
SR. SHIN HU-YE
Hello?
¿Aló?
Can we meet this afternoon?
¿Podemos vernos hoy?
Would you like to order?
¿Desea ordenar?
2 AMERICANOS, REGULAR, WEAK
2 AMERICANOS, NORMAL, SUAVE
"Two Americanos, regular, weak." Is that correct?
Dos americanos, uno normal y otro suave, ¿correcto?
That prick said
El imbécil dijo
we can't do anything to him...
que no le podemos hacer nada porque somos dioses de la vida.
Why? What was that about?
¿Por qué hizo eso?
I have to ask him.
Tengo que preguntarle
I can't ask him.
No puedo preguntarle.
Yes?
¿Sí?
Ms. Yun is here, sir.
La señorita Yun, señor.
Have a seat here.
Toma asiento aquí.
-Is it awkward for you to be here? -Yes.
- ¿Se siente incómoda? - Sí.
You'll get used to it because you'll be coming here often.
Ya se acostumbrará al venir más seguido.
-Pardon? -The contract has been canceled.
- ¿Cómo? - Cancelaron el contrato.
Some objected, but I told them you'll pay the early termination fee.
Se opusieron, pero les dije que pagaría una multa.
Thank you.
Gracias.
But regarding the early termination fee, I can't--
Pero con respecto a la multa…
Half of it can be paid with your skill set.
Puede pagar la mitad con sus habilidades.
With my skill set?
¿Con mis habilidades?
Hotel management falls under the service sector.
Trabajamos en el sector de servicios.
It requires a lot of emotional labor,
Exige mucho trabajo emocional, en especial para los operadores,
They always have to put customers above themselves.
porque siempre deben priorizar a los clientes.
Please help my employees better cope with their work-related stress.
¿Podría enseñarle a mis empleados a manejar su estrés?
I'm thinking one session per week would be good.
Creo que una sesión por semana estaría bien.
Sure. Then the other half--
Claro, pero la otra mitad…
Thirty percent of it can be paid through the farm.
Puede pagar un 30 % en la granja.
You said I could ask you if I ever needed help at the farm.
Dijo que podía pedirle ayuda para eso.
I wasn't going to pay you at all for your labor,
No le pagaré por el trabajo,
but I'll deduct the amount from the early termination fee.
pero sí lo deduciré de la multa.
As for the 20 percent that's left,
Y sobre el 20 % restante,
-you can pay it off by treating me. -Sorry?
- puede tratarme a mí. - ¿Qué?
I still suffer from insomnia.
Aún sufro de insomnio.
Book me in for the day after tomorrow, in the afternoon.
Puedo pasar mañana.
I'll pay for your work at the farm and my sessions out of my own pocket.
Pagaré por su trabajo de la granja y las consultas
The money will be sent directly to Beriwon under your name.
y se lo enviaré a Beriwon bajo su nombre.
Where is he?
¿Dónde estará?
-I'm here. -My gosh!
- Aquí estoy. - Dios mío.
Where did he come from?
¿De dónde salió?
Come here.
Ven aquí.
-What's the matter? -I have a question for you.
- ¿Qué pasa? - Tengo una pregunta.
Go ahead.
Dime.
What happened to your eyes?
¿Qué les pasó a tus ojos?
Sit down.
Siéntate.
What is it?
¿Qué pasa?
Did you attend the service last Sunday?
¿Fuiste a misa el domingo?
Of course. Do you want to start attending my church?
Claro. ¿Quieres ir a mi iglesia?
Just find a church near you.
- Encuentra una más cercana. - No, no es eso.
Were they there too?
¿También fueron?
-Do you need dating advice? -No!
- ¿Necesitas consejos para citas? - ¡No!
This isn't about dating.
No se trata de eso.
I'm just curious about something.
Solo tengo una pregunta.
Well, why would a guy suddenly hug a girl from behind?
¿Por qué un hombre abrazaría a una chica por detrás?
-I'd call it sexual harassment. -No! It's...
- Eso es acoso sexual. - ¡No!
-It's not like that. -Did someone hug you?
- No fue así. - ¿Te abrazaron?
You should've turned and punched him.
Debiste golpearlo.
No, hear me out. He's not that kind of guy!
No, escúchame. No es esa clase de hombre.
What I'm saying is...
Lo que quiero decir…
I just want to know why Mr. Shin hugged me from behind.
¿Por qué el señor Shin me abrazó por detrás?
My goodness.
Dios mío.
You seemed a bit unstable yesterday.
Ayer te veías inestable.
You should get more sleep.
Deberías descansar más.
Hey, you don't believe me?
Oye, ¿acaso no me crees?
Oh, no. What do I do? My gosh.
Cielos, ¿qué hago?
Hold on.
Espera.
Do you know her?
¿La conoces?
Why are they walking together?
¿Por qué están caminando juntos?
Right, I guess you haven't heard the news yet.
Supongo que aún no te has enterado.
The Block World contract...
El proyecto de Block World fue cancelado.
What?
¿Qué?
I can't believe this.
No puedo creerlo.
They're moving it to Chungcheong Province?
¿Lo harán en Chungcheong?
-Because of So-a? -Hello?
- ¿Por So-a? - ¿Aló?
Grandpa, do you own any land in Chungcheong Province?
Abuelo, ¿tienes terrenos en Chungcheong?
It's a good thing.
Es algo bueno.
Actually, I've never been this lucky in my whole life.
De hecho, nunca había tenido tanta suerte.
I'll be busy for the first time in a while.
Al menos estaré ocupada.
Why doesn't she want to sell that land?
¿Por qué no quiere vender el terreno?
How would I know?
Yo qué sé.
What did you say about that land?
¿No habías dicho que nadie quería comprar ese terreno?
That's right, sir.
Así es, señor.
I heard it had been for sale
Oí que estuvo a la venta barato durante mucho tiempo.
And they offered her a lot
Y le ofrecieron bastante
because a new road will be built there.
porque construirían un nuevo camino ahí.
I don't understand what her problem is.
No sé qué habrá pasado.
Please excuse me, sir. I have to take this call.
Disculpe, señor. Tengo que contestar.
Do you own any land in Chungcheong Province or not?
¿Tienes terrenos en Chungcheong o no?
They'll find another site.
Encontrarán otro sitio.
I have no land in Chungcheong Province.
No tengo terrenos ahí.
What?
¿Qué?
You always said you own land all over the country.
Siempre has dicho que tienes terrenos por todo el país.
Why don't you own any in Chungcheong Province?
¿Por qué no en Chungcheong?
Why haven't you bought any land there all these years?
¿Por qué no compraste ahí en todos estos años?
Sir. According to Mr. Lee at Beriwon,
Señor.
she had agreed to sell the land and even signed the contract.
había aceptado vender el terreno e incluso firmó el contrato,
But then she suddenly changed her mind.
pero cambió de parecer.
What? Why?
¿Qué? ¿Por qué?
Because of leopard poop.
Por caca de leopardo.
What?
¿Qué?
-Yes, leopard poop. -What's he saying?
- Sí, caca de leopardo. - ¿Qué?
Sang-yu, I'm picking up a part-time job starting today.
Encontré un trabajo de medio tiempo.
Dr. Yun.
Dra. Yun.
What brings you here?
¿Qué haces aquí?
Had I known I could find you here, I would've caused a scene long ago.
De haber sabido que estabas aquí, hubiera venido antes.
-What? -I had forgotten
¿Qué?
You were so stuck-up, even though you had nothing.
Eras una engreída aunque no tenías nada.
You pretended to be so innocent and naive
Fingías ser inocente
and enjoyed all the attention you got.
y disfrutabas la atención.
"I'm different. I'm special."
"Soy diferente. Soy especial".
You were always so condescending
Siempre fuiste tan condescendiente y pretenciosa.
Hey, who are you talking about?
Oye, ¿de quién estás hablando?
I had forgotten all about it,
Lo había olvidado,
but that guy reminded me.
pero él me lo recordó.
Isn't he one of the beggars that used to freeload off your family?
¿No es uno de los mendigos que se aprovechaban de tu familia?
Hey, watch your mouth.
Oye, cuidado con lo que dices.
You're not selling your land because of leopard poop?
- ¿No venderás el terreno por caca? - ¿Qué?
This is exactly why I can't stand you.
Es por esto que no te soporto.
Who cares about leopard poop?
¿A quién le importa la caca de leopardo?
You can't even pay your rent.
No puedes ni pagar la renta. ¿En verdad puedes darte ese lujo?
What is that annoying voice?
¿Y esa voz tan molesta?
Wait.
Espera.
-Aren't you Shin Ja-ya? -Jo Yeom-mi?
- ¿Shin Ja-ya? - ¿Jo Yeom-mi?
It's been a long time, but I'm not happy to see you.
Tanto tiempo. No me alegra verte. ¿Qué haces aquí?
Everyone's here.
Todos están aquí.
The beggar, the stuck-up, and the fortune-teller.
El mendigo, la engreída y la vidente.
Is this a countryside market or something?
¿Estamos en una feria rural o algo así?
Hey, what's that called? Oh, right.
Sí, ya me imagino.
If we had a street singer here, it'd be just perfect.
Solo falta un cantante callejero y sería perfecto.
Ja-ya, are you bipolar? Why are you so worked up?
Ja-ya, ¿eres bipolar? ¿Por qué estás tan alterada?
Ja-ya, you...
Ja-ya, tienes…
What?
¿Qué?
A long-haired woman is sitting on your back.
…una mujer sentada en tu espalda.
There's a child on your leg too.
Y un niño en tu pierna.
He has no nose.
No tiene nariz.
And an old lady is standing over there.
Y hay una anciana parada ahí.
My gosh!
¡Dios mío!
Let's go.
Vamos.
-Get us something to drink. -Okay.
- Tráenos algo de beber. - Bien.
What was that about?
¿Qué fue eso?
Grandpa, kick her out.
Abuelo, échala.
You brat, who are you to tell me what to do?
¿Quién te crees para decirme qué hacer?
Your building is haunted.
El edificio está embrujado.
What? Cut it out!
¿Qué?
Get back here right now!
¡Regresa ahora!
Oh, dear.
Cielos.
It's so strange.
Esto es muy extraño. ¿Cómo se habrá enterado?
And how does she know about my rent situation?
¿Y cómo sabe de mi renta?
Is she stalking me?
¿Me estará siguiendo?
Why is she being so nosy?
Pero qué entrometida.
By the way, she's becoming prettier by the day.
Y cada día se ve más linda.
Hey, do I seem pretentious?
Oye, ¿te parezco pretenciosa?
Do I enjoy getting attention while pretending to be all naive?
¿Me gusta llamar la atención?
Do I act like I'm special or better than others?
¿Actúo como si fuera mejor que los demás?
What did I do?
¿Qué hice?
How would I know what you were like in high school?
- Es lo que hiciste en secundaria. - ¿En secundaria?
Think about it. She's talking about your high school days.
Piénsalo, a eso se refiere.
It's not about something you did.
Y no es algo que hiciste,
I bet she's upset about something you didn't do.
debe ser algo que no hiciste.
You know, there are those kids who always get good grades,
Hay personas que obtienen buenas notas aunque no estudien.
They get on your nerves because they never study. It's like that.
Y eso les molesta a algunos.
Hey, I studied so hard back in school.
Oye, yo estudié muy duro.
That's not what I'm talking about.
No me refiero a eso.
What brings you here out of the blue?
¿Y a qué viniste?
Why did you show up in my dream out of the blue?
¿Por qué apareciste en mi sueño?
-What? -I've seen all kinds of people
- ¿Qué? - He soñado con muchas personas,
This morning, you showed up in my dream
Hoy te apareciste en mi sueño y te reíste como una loca.
So I was wondering if you have any good news to share.
¿Tienes alguna noticia que quieras compartir conmigo?
But I have to say, you seem a little down today.
Debo decir que te ves un poco desanimada.
Is something wrong?
¿Pasó algo?
No.
No.
I'm just trying to solve a very difficult math problem.
Estoy intentando resolver un problema matemático.
-You used to be good at math. -Yes, you're right.
- Te iba bien en matemáticas. - Sí.
But this problem scares me a little.
Pero este problema me asusta un poco.
The answer is already there,
Ya conozco la respuesta,
but the problem-solving process doesn't match the answer.
pero el proceso no coincide con ella.
Then the process must be wrong.
Entonces el proceso debe estar mal.
Right, it is wrong.
Así es.
So, I have to find another value of X now.
Así que debo encontrar otro valor para X.
A value that will help me arrive at the answer without hurting anyone.
Uno que me dé la respuesta sin herir a nadie.
I'm not following at all.
No te entiendo,
One thing is for sure. Math didn't do anything wrong.
pero sé que las matemáticas no tienen la culpa.
She's right.
Tiene razón.
No one is guilty, including me and him.
No es culpa de nadie.
No innocent person should be punished.
Ninguna persona inocente debería ser castigada.
So, I'm just going to blame math, knowing it's completely innocent.
Así que culparé a las matemáticas, sabiendo que no tienen la culpa.
I'll find a brilliant, creative solution.
Encontraré una solución brillante y creativa.
A solution that will impress everyone.
Una solución que impresionará a todos.
One that will help me arrive at the answer
Una que me dé la respuesta
without hurting anyone.
sin lastimar a nadie.
What's going on?
¿Qué pasa?
You said you were done with trying to get your powers back.
¿No te habías rendido a recuperar tus poderes?
You sounded so determined.
Parecías tan decidido.
Let's go.
Vamos.
So-a.
So-a.
I've been trying...
Estuve todo el día
to solve a math problem all day. You know what math is, right?
intentando resolver un problema matemático.
I have to find the value of X,
Debo hallar el valor de X,
but I can't use any of the existing formulas.
pero no puedo usar las fórmulas conocidas.
So, I struggled all day to come up with a new formula,
Así que intenté hallar una nueva fórmula
and I've finally found the answer.
y finalmente lo logré.
The answer is...
La respuesta es…
stopping here.
…detenerse aquí.
The answer was already decided for us.
La respuesta ya estaba decidida.
It's time for us to wrap things up
Es hora de terminar las cosas en vez de empezar algo nuevo.
I've asked myself how I should end things.
Me pregunté cómo debería hacerlo.
The ending should be beautiful. We should end things on a positive note.
Debería ser un final bonito.
Help me out here.
Ayúdame.
Only then...
Solo así
can I live as a lesser, not a loser.
podré vivir como una luchadora.
Then...
Entonces,
what do you want me to do?
¿qué quieres que haga?
Treat me like...
Trátame como lo hacías
you used to before yesterday.
antes de ayer.
Let's go.
Vamos.
-You're heading out early again? -Yes.
- ¿Te vas tan temprano? - Sí.
The clinic now opens two hours earlier.
Abriremos la clínica dos horas antes.
I had to change the hours to sort out someone's mess.
Tuve que hacerlo para arreglar los problemas de alguien.
-What do you mean? -It's better that you don't know.
- ¿Cómo? - Es mejor que no lo sepas.
Even if you knew,
Y aunque lo supieras,
there wouldn't really be anything that you could do.
no habría nada que pudieras hacer.
Those smug eyes of yours are making me want to challenge you.
Esos arrogantes ojos tuyos me hacen querer desafiarte.
Fine. I'll do everything in my power to help you until I leave.
Pero haré lo posible por ayudarte hasta que me vaya.
-What do you need? -Money?
¿Qué necesitas?
Forget what I just said.
Olvida lo que dije.
Shouldn't we throw a farewell party for you before you leave?
Deberíamos hacerte una fiesta de despedida.
Treat me to a nice meal.
Invítame a cenar.
You'll become a king soon.
Pronto serás rey.
I can't because I have no money.
No tengo dinero.
Gosh, then why don't you go earn some money?
- ¿Y por qué no ganas algo? - ¿Qué?
HABAEK YUN SO-A
HABAEK, YUN SO-A
Isn't the human world a pretty fun place?
¿No es divertido el mundo humano?
The High Priest said the exact same thing.
El sumo sacerdote dijo lo mismo.
Is it because of that girl?
¿Es por la chica?
Is that why you don't look happy, even after finding the sacred stone?
¿Por eso no estás feliz, incluso con la piedra sagrada?
And is that why Mura seems so anxious?
¿Y por eso Mura está ansiosa?
I can understand Mura.
Entiendo a Mura.
While you were going through that,
Mientras pasabas por eso,
we were as sad and distressed as you were.
estábamos tan tristes y angustiados como tú.
And Mura hated that woman to begin with, you know.
Y Mura odiaba a esa mujer, ¿sabías?
-Enough. -But you know what?
- Suficiente. - Pero ¿sabes qué?
You're probably not aware of it,
Probablemente no lo sepas,
but I've always been on your side.
pero siempre estuve de tu lado.
You've always made the right choices,
Siempre has tomado las decisiones correctas,
even if they ended in tragedy.
aunque terminen en tragedia.
Do you know what the core difference between humans and us is?
¿Sabes qué nos diferencia de los humanos?
Humans live such short lives. That's why they can avoid harsh criticism at times,
Los humanos tienen vidas muy cortas.
Especially when it's done out of love for someone.
En especial si es por amor.
They gladly hold even red-hot stones
Pueden aguantar lo que sea
when they realize that life is very short,
cuando se dan cuenta de eso.
saying "Life is so short."
Y dicen: "La vida es tan corta".
Well, that girl is an exception, though.
Bueno, esa chica es la excepción.
Now, shall we talk about why you're hesitating?
Ahora, ¿hablamos de tus dudas?
Is what you're feeling now...
¿Qué sientes por los humanos?
sympathy towards humans or love?
¿Compasión o amor?
You're not sure.
No estás seguro.
But you know what? That's how it began for you even back then.
Pero ¿sabes qué?
And the end of it...
Y al final
was nothing but disgrace.
terminó en desgracia.
Even that, I support. I've already told you.
Te apoyé incluso en eso. Ya te lo dije.
Mura said she'd treat me to a delicious lunch today.
Mura dijo que me invitaría a comer un rico almuerzo hoy.
I wonder where she'll take me.
¿A dónde me llevará?
-Can we really be doing this? -I don't know.
- ¿Podemos hacer esto? - No sé.
Answer me. Who is that guy?
Dime, ¿quién es ese tipo?
I actually want to punch Biryeom more than that guy.
Quiero golpear a Biryeom más que a ese tipo.
Don't say things like that! He might hear us.
¡No digas eso! Podría escucharnos.
Why can't he do it himself?
¿Por qué no lo hace él?
-Gosh. -My gosh!
- Cielos. - ¡Dios mío!
What's going on? Isn't he human?
¿Qué pasa? ¿No es humano?
I'm not sure. He must be human, though.
No sé, pero debe serlo.
Look at all the blood.
Mira toda esa sangre. ¿Qué quiere?
Wait! It's me.
¡Espera! ¡Soy yo!
Isn't that Jugeollin?
¿Jugeollin?
Get out of here!
¡Váyanse de aquí!
Come on. Let's get out of here!
¡Vamos! ¡Escapemos de aquí!
I visited those lowly deities
Visité a esos dioses menores para conseguir comida,
I overheard them talking about this place, so I followed them just in case.
Los oí hablar de este lugar, así que los seguí.
You're bleeding a lot.
Estás sangrando mucho.
Why on earth did they do this to me?
¿Por qué me hicieron esto?
I sent them.
Yo los envié.
That's right. We're different from you.
Así es. Somos diferentes a ti.
That's us.
Así somos nosotros.
But those who just beat you up
Pero los que te golpearon
are at the bottom of the barrel.
son lo peor de lo peor.
They have no interest in returning,
No les interesa regresar y no tienen nada que perder.
It's not enough to get back at you for what you did to my friend,
No compensa lo que le hiciste a mi amigo, pero digamos que estamos a mano.
And...
Y otra cosa,
if you forget your place and threaten me one more time,
si te atreves a amenazarme de nuevo,
I certainly won't let it slide.
te aseguro que no te lo perdonaré.
Why are you doing this to me?
¿Por qué me haces esto?
Why?
¿Por qué?
Don't look at me like that.
No me mires así.
Just because you don't want to get your revenge
Solo porque no quieras vengarte no significa que deba perdonarlo.
What on earth are you doing at this barbaric place?
¿Qué haces en este lugar tan salvaje?
Hey, you.
Hola.
Give this a try.
Si pruebas esto,
Then you'll learn how petty our powers are.
entenderás lo insignificantes que son nuestros poderes.
Since when did he stop talking?
¿Desde cuándo dejó de hablar?
Ever since you froze his tongue and crushed it.
Desde que le congelaste la lengua.
But he has a twin brother.
Pero tiene un hermano gemelo.
Was his name Momyeong?
¿Momyeong?
Didn't he come with him?
¿No vino con él?
Actually, I haven't seen him for hundreds of years.
De hecho, hace siglos que no lo veo.
Let's go.
Vamos.
I don't think it's a good idea to meet him.
No creo que sea buena idea ir a verlo.
You said you'd never become a dark person.
Dijiste que nunca te convertirías una persona mala.
Hu-ye.
Hu-ye.
Hey, be careful! You're going to cross the centerline.
¡Cuidado, vas a cruzar la línea central!
How does it feel to eat because of hunger...
¿Cómo es comer por hambre
compared to when you used to eat just for fun?
en vez de comer solo por diversión?
That's why you should return soon.
Por eso deberías regresar.
It doesn't look like he wants to go back.
No parece que quiera hacerlo.
Hey.
¿Aló?
What? A house?
¿Qué? ¿Una casa?
No, just cancel it.
No, solo cancélalo.
Excuse me.
Disculpen.
Our servant must be very persuasive.
Nuestra sirvienta debe ser muy persuasiva.
I heard he gave the land back to her.
Oí que le devolvieron el terreno.
The project went down the drain,
Cancelaron el proyecto,
and many board members are angry about what happened.
lo cual enfadó a la junta directiva.
What? What are you talking about?
¿Qué? ¿De qué estás hablando?
How is it that you always know everything?
¿Cómo es que siempre lo sabes todo?
I don't have much to do, you know.
No tengo mucho que hacer.
From the way he acted,
Por la forma en que actuó,
it didn't seem like he'd give up the land so easily.
no creí que renunciaría al terreno tan fácilmente.
I wonder how So-a managed to convince a guy like him.
¿Cómo lo habrá convencido?
I can see that the land isn't the issue.
Sé que el terreno no es el problema.
If you don't want to do the dirty work yourself,
Si no te quieres ensuciar las manos, solo avísame.
I know of many ways to harm him.
Puedo herirlo de muchas formas.
Why is he so twisted?
¿Por qué es tan perverso?
He was always like that.
Siempre ha sido así.
Why? Did he cause trouble again?
¿Está creando problemas?
I have no idea what they're talking about.
No tengo idea de qué están hablando.
They're making me feel so left out.
Me hacen sentir excluido.
So? When are you planning to return?
¿Entonces? ¿Cuándo planeas regresar?
Jeez.
Cielos.
Are you a broken record?
¿De nuevo con lo mismo?
Stop saying the same thing over and over again. It's annoying.
Deja de repetir lo mismo siempre. Es molesto.
He's not a kid. He'll return when the time comes.
No es un niño. Regresará cuando sea la hora.
I'm sure he knows...
Seguro sabe lo que le pasará si no regresa.
I'm off.
Ya me voy.
-You said you have to go somewhere. -Yes, it'll take a few days.
- ¿Dijiste que te ibas? - Sí, volveré pronto.
Stay until I come back. Don't leave before then.
No te vayas hasta que regrese.
-You don't need to wait for him. -See you when you're back.
- No necesitas esperarlo. - Nos vemos.
From the way he acted,
Por la forma en que actuó,
it didn't seem like he'd give up the land so easily.
no creí que renunciaría al terreno tan fácilmente.
I wonder how So-a managed to convince a guy like him.
¿Cómo lo habrá convencido?
She'll become...
Se convertirá en el deseo más grande que he tenido
since my life in this world began.
desde que comenzó mi vida en este mundo.
What kind of nonsense are you saying right now?
¿Qué tonterías estás diciendo?
-She is a divine servant. -So what?
- Es una sirvienta divina. - ¿Y qué?
You said you're going to return to your world.
Dijiste que regresarías a tu mundo.
Ms. Yun referred to you as a wind that's passing by.
Además, se refirió a ti como una brisa pasajera.
No.
No.
She said that the wind has stopped blowing.
Como una brisa que dejó de soplar.
Why do you keep acting like that towards Habaek?
¿Por qué actúas así con Habaek?
You're one incorrigible jerk.
Eres un tonto sin remedio.
You haven't changed one bit since you were little.
No has cambiado desde que eras pequeño.
You've always been so rude, irresponsible, and bullheaded.
Siempre has sido irresponsable y terco.
Don't you think you're overreacting?
¿No estás exagerando?
I can say things like that to Habaek, considering our relationship.
Puedo tratarlo así por nuestra relación.
That's exactly what I mean.
A eso me refiero.
Habaek is letting it slide because it's between you and him.
Te lo perdona solo porque eres tú.
If you were just a lowly deity,
Si fueras una deidad menor,
and if this wasn't a quarrel between you and Habaek,
si no fueras tú,
the Land of Water would never forgive you for being so rude.
no te perdonarían tal insolencia.
Are you mad because I provoked Habaek?
¿Estás enojada porque provoqué a Habaek
Or is it because Habaek might
o porque Habaek podría usar eso
use what I said as an excuse and stay here until the very last day?
como excusa para quedarse aquí hasta el último día?
Stop beating around the bush and get straight to the point.
Déjate de rodeos y ve directo al grano.
Don't act all mature like you used to in the old days.
No finjas ser madura como lo hacías antes.
What do you mean?
¿A qué te refieres?
Admit that you feel insecure because of So-a.
So-a te hace sentir insegura.
You're worried that Habaek might already like her.
Te preocupa que Habaek la quiera.
You've lost him once. I know you don't want to lose him again.
Sé que no quieres volver a perderlo.
Just be honest and ask me for help,
Sé sincera y pídeme ayuda, como siempre lo hiciste.
I'm also fond of So-a,
También me agrada So-a, pero siempre te preferiré a ti.
So, don't worry and just say you need my help.
Así que solo pídeme ayuda.
I can do many things.
Puedo hacer muchas cosas.
Biryeom... why are you being like this?
¿Por qué estás…
You see,
Siempre has actuado
you always acted as you pleased,
de la forma que querías,
but you were never this anxious.
pero nunca te comportaste así.
Is it Shin Hu-ye?
¿Es por Shin Hu-ye?
Have you changed because of that halfie? That's it, isn't it?
Ese dios menor te hizo cambiar, ¿cierto?
What did he do...
¿Qué hizo
to provoke you?
para provocarte?
There must be something I don't know about.
¿Qué no me estás diciendo?
Thank you, young man.
Gracias, joven.
Wait up.
Espera.
Wait a second.
Un momento.
My gosh, this is a nice one.
Vaya, qué buen lugar.
Oh, boy.
Cielos.
Yes, that's it. Over there.
Eso es. Por ahí.
SCRAP METAL, PAPER, USED CLOTHES
CENTRO DE RECICLAJE
Here.
Toma.
You worked hard, so you deserve to get paid.
Trabajaste duro. Te lo mereces.
My goodness.
Dios mío.
You've never worked before, right?
¿Nunca habías trabajado? Debe ser tu primer sueldo.
I've lived long enough, so I can see through most people.
He vivido mucho, así que puedo notar esas cosas.
People usually buy red long johns
Algunos les hacen regalos a sus padres con su primer sueldo.
But you don't have parents, do you?
Pero no tienes padres, ¿cierto?
Always do your best.
Si das lo mejor de ti,
Then, eventually, something amazing will fall into your lap.
con el tiempo, algo bueno te caerá del cielo.
A while ago, I found a diamond ring
Hace un tiempo, encontré un anillo de diamantes
and took it to a police officer.
y se lo llevé a la policía.
I'll be happy if the owner shows up,
Estaré feliz si aparece el dueño
and I'll be even happier if no one claims it.
y lo estaré aún más si nadie lo reclama.
Come have a look.
Eche un vistazo.
Aren't they cute?
¿No son lindas?
My friend and I designed them together.
Las diseñamos con un amigo.
This.
Esto.
They say that drinking from chipped mugs can bring bad luck.
Beber de tazas rotas trae mala suerte.
Is this enough?
¿Me alcanza?
No, it's not.
No es suficiente.
100 PERCENT HANDMADE
100 % HECHO A MANO
Do you want a photo of me holding it?
¿Quieres sacarme fotos?
Can we book your appointment for next Wednesday?
¿Podría agendarla para el miércoles?
Sure. I'll see you next week, then.
- Claro. Nos vemos. - Bien.
Wednesday.
Miércoles.
-She's booked for next Wednesday, right? -Yes.
- ¿La agendaste para el miércoles? - Sí.
-We'll be able to pay this month's rent. -Really?
- Podremos pagar la renta este mes. - ¿Sí?
Mr. Ma recommended our clinic to many of his acquaintances.
El Sr. Ma nos recomendó a muchas personas.
All the new patients we've been getting these days are his acquaintances.
De ahí vienen los nuevos pacientes.
WATER DEMON
DEMONIO DEL AGUA
Are you not going to answer it?
¿No vas a contestar?
Hello?
¿Aló?
-One iced Americano, please. -Sure.
Un americano frío.
One iced latte, please.
Un latte frío, por favor.
Why does he keep looking around like a little kid?
¿Por qué mira todo como un niño?
He must be really curious about something.
Debe estar curioso por algo.
Now, I can tell just by looking at him.
Puedo notarlo solo con verlo.
Why were you looking around?
¿Qué estabas mirando?
-Do you want something to drink? -No, thanks.
- ¿Quieres probar algo? - No, gracias.
Then I'll just order whatever.
Pediré lo que sea.
One Americano and one iced Americano, please.
Un americano normal y un americano frío, por favor.
-Here's your coffee. -Thank you.
- Aquí tiene. - Gracias.
What's this? Why is this water black?
¿Y esta agua? ¿Por qué está negra?
I see other drinks with nice colors.
Otras tienen colores lindos.
-You seemed curious. -Me?
- Te veías curioso. - ¿Yo?
That's not true.
Eso no es cierto.
Maybe I was just thinking it's weird.
Estaba pensando que es raro.
There are so many other colors.
Hay muchos otros colores. ¿Por qué me diste esta agua negra?
You're so chatty today.
Estás muy hablador hoy.
You're never this chatty, so you rambling on like this
Nunca hablas tanto.
probably means there's something you want to tell me,
Debes querer decirme algo,
and you're hesitating to say it for some reason.
pero estás dudando por alguna razón.
-Isn't it too bitter for you? -It is.
- ¿Está muy amargo? - Sí.
It's bitter and sour, but I also taste a little bit of sweetness.
Es amargo y ácido, pero también un poco dulce.
You have a sensitive palate.
Qué buen paladar.
It tastes unusual, but not bad. I should come here often.
No está mal. Debería venir más seguido.
Jeez, whatever. So, what is it that you want to tell me?
Como sea.
What is this?
¿Qué es esto?
Is this for me?
¿Es para mí?
Is this a gift?
- ¿Es un regalo? - Las tazas rotas traen mala suerte.
Don't be so touched by this.
No te emociones tanto.
I'm only trying to help you know your place.
Es para que lo entiendas.
-What? -Watch.
- ¿Qué? - Mira.
This is you.
Esta eres tú.
You're wagging your tail because you saw your master.
Mueve la cola porque vio a su amo.
This is your master.
Este es el amo
-And you, the servant. -"The servant"?
- y la sirvienta. - ¿La sirvienta?
So, this is you?
¿Este eres tú?
Yes. This is probably getting you all riled up.
Sí, ¿eso te molesta?
Hence the name Yongyong the Angry Dragon. I came up with that name.
La llamé Yongyong, la dragona enojada.
I want you to remember that you're my servant every time you use it.
Te recordará que eres mi sirvienta.
Goodness!
Dios mío.
You're embarrassing me.
Me estás avergonzando.
Then what's this? Does this mean that you're going to be my servant?
¿Qué es esto entonces? ¿Significa que serás mi sirviente?
Yongyong.
Yongyong.
-Yongyong. -Give it back.
Devuélveme eso.
Hey, it's mine.
Oye, eso es mío.
You can't take them back. They're mine now.
No puedes retractarte. Ahora son mías.
Where did you get the money to buy these?
¿Cómo las compraste?
Did Namsuri give you some spending money?
¿Namsuri te dio dinero?
I worked two part-time jobs.
Hice dos trabajos de medio tiempo.
You did what?
¿Qué hiciste qué?
You collected waste cardboard and sold it?
¿Recolectaste cartones?
And...
Y también…
I let people take photos of me.
…me tomaron fotos.
They gave me a few as a souvenir.
Hasta me regalaron algunas.
Are you touched?
¿Te conmoviste?
Yes, I'm so touched.
Así es.
And this plush toy is so cute.
Qué peluche tan lindo.
I have to go.
Debo irme.
What? I just said that it's cute.
¿Qué? Solo dije que era lindo.
I can't even say it's cute?
¿No puedo decir eso?
Yongyong. Leave my cups at my place, okay?
Yongyong, deja mis tazas en casa, ¿sí?
He's so unobservant.
Qué despistado.
How did he not notice it while taking the photos?
¿Cómo no vio el peluche antes?
I guess he only sees what he wants to see.
Solo nota lo que quiere ver.
Dr. Yun, I'm off.
Dra. Yun, me voy.
Will you really be okay?
¿Estarás bien?
Why don't you ask Mr. Shin to come half an hour early?
¿Por qué el Sr. Shin no viene más temprano?
-Just go. -It's just that Hyeong-sik--
- Vete. - Es que Hyeong-sik…
I said just go.
- Que te vayas. - Nos vemos mañana.
He always uses Hyeong-sik as an excuse.
Siempre menciona a Hyeong-sik. Al menos preséntamelo.
DR. YUN SO-A
DRA. YUN SO-A
if you forget your place and threaten me one more time,
Si te atreves a amenazarme de nuevo,
I certainly won't let it slide.
te aseguro que no te lo perdonaré.
Habaek is just as you saw. And as for me, it's pretty simple.
Ya viste cómo es Habaek. Por mi parte, es bastante simple.
I hate you.
Te odio.
And I will continue to hate you very much.
Y te seguiré odiando mucho.
Because...
¿Es porque soy diferente a ustedes?
Let's just say that, halfie.
Digamos que sí, dios menor.
I heard all you can do is destroy people and things.
Oí que lo único que puedes hacer es destruir.
You don't like gods.
No te gustan los dioses.
I heard you've killed a few.
Hasta oí que mataste algunos.
That's not true.
Eso no es cierto.
Did you want to prove that you're a god too,
¿Querías probar que también eras uno, dios menor?
DR. YUN SO-A
DRA. YUN SO-A
I wonder if he's okay.
¿Estará bien?
Did you come alone?
¿Viniste solo?
May I join you?
¿Puedo acompañarte?
DR. YUN SO-A
DRA. YUN SO-A
Hello?
¿Aló?
Mr. Shin, why aren't you here yet?
Señor Shin, ¿por qué no ha llegado?
I'm sorry.
Lo siento.
Shall we reschedule your appointment if you can't make it today?
Podemos reagendar si no puede venir hoy.
No, I'll leave now. I'm sorry.
No, voy en camino. Lo siento.
Is he under the weather?
¿Se sentirá mal?
When do you plan to return to the Land of Water?
¿Cuándo planea regresar?
Are you really going to wait until Lord Judong comes back?
¿Va a esperar al señor Judong?
I guess Ms. Descendant is coming home late today.
La Srta. Descendiente llegará tarde hoy.
WATER DEMON
DEMONIO DEL AGUA
-Hello? -Why aren't you coming home?
- ¿Aló? - ¿Por qué no has llegado?
I'm still at work. My last patient is running late.
Mi último paciente se retrasó.
He'll be here soon, so I'll--
Llegará pronto, así que…
Mr. Shin. I have to go.
Señor Shin. Tengo que irme.
Mr. Shin.
Señor Shin.
Did he drink and drive?
¿Condujo ebrio?
Try to sober up. My gosh!
Intente controlarse. Dios mío.
-Give me some money. -Pardon?
- Dame dinero. - ¿Perdón?
Mr. Shin.
Señor Shin.
Please wake up.
Por favor, despierte.
What should I do?
¿Qué hago?
I can't give him a fever reducer because he's been drinking.
No puedo tratar su fiebre porque bebió.
We don't care either.
Tampoco nos importa.
However, there's something I need to check.
Pero hay algo que debo comprobar.
If what I'm thinking is right,
Si lo que pienso es correcto,
you'll be proving that you are indeed the legendary monster.
probarás que eres el monstruo legendario.
His fever isn't going down.
No le baja la fiebre.
What are you talking about?
¿De qué hablas?
Mr. Shin...
Señor Shin.
Ms. Yun.
Señorita Yun.
I'm sorry.
Lo siento.
Can I be irresponsible?
¿Puedo ser irresponsable?
-What are we? -You asked me what we are.
- ¿Qué somos? - Tú preguntaste.
-Does someone like me... -If I must ask a favor of you...
¿Alguien como yo…?
Does someone like me...
¿Alguien como yo
-Should I ask you to make him stay... -...deserve a woman like her?
- ¿Te pediría que hagas que se quede - se la merece?
...or let him go?
o que se vaya?
-I want to hold you in my arms... -You may not.
- Quiero abrazarte - No puedes.
and kiss you.
y besarte.
Let's just stay like this.
Quedémonos así.
However much I think about it, my answer is no.
Aunque lo piense mucho, mi respuesta es no.
-I want you to be my first... -I'm asking you to let Habaek go.
- Quiero que seas mi primera - Deja ir a Habaek.
...and last.
y mi última.
That fool is in love with you.
Ese tonto se enamoró de ti.
So would it be okay to begin?
¿Podría empezar?